The story I want to tell you about, started to me,
القصة التي أريد أن أخبركم عنها حدثت لي
in 1996 when I was studying in England.
في 1996 عندما كنت أدرس في انجلترا
One day, I was glancing through my bank statement (I didn't have much to look at)
يوما ما كنت ألقي نظرة على حسابي البنكي (لم يكن لدي الكثير لأراه)
and I've noticed that in the upper corner there was a symbol, that I'm going to show you,
ولاحظت أن في أعلى الورقة رمزًا, سأعرضه لكم
saying that document had been made in plain language, for me to understand it.
موضحا أن الوثيقة كتبت باللغة المبسطة، من أجلي حتى أفهمها
The idea interested me; I tried to find out what that was
أثارت الفكرة إهتمامي، حاولت ان أعرف ما هذا
and I found out that there was a campaign for the simplification of language,
وأكتشفت أن هناك حملة لتبسيط اللغة
which was the "Plain English Campaign".
معروفة ب " حملة الانجليزي المبسط"
I thought it was a fabulous idea, for about one day or two,
ليوم او اثنين تقريبا، ظننتها فكرة رائعة
and I've never thought about it since.
ولم أفكر في هذا الأمر بعدها
When I came back to Portugal, for good,
عندما عدت للبرتغال،لحسن الحظ
I came across with several documents - for example, my work contract,
وجدت العديد من الوثائق- مثلاً: عقد عملي
the papers I had to sign to buy a house, the electricity bill --
الأوراق التي وقعتها لأشتري منزلاً فاتورة الكهرباء --
a series of documents that reminded me of that bank statement.
ذكرتني مجموعة من الوثائق، بحسابي البنكي
Not because they were equally clear and simple,
ليس لأنه كلهم كانوا بنفس الوضوح والبساطة
but because they were the exact opposite.
لكن لأنهم كانوا على نقيض تماما.
Because I had to read everything twice or thrice, to begin to understand what was written there.
لأنني اضطررت أن أقرأ كل شئ مرتين أو ثلاث حتى أبدأ في إستيعاب المكتوب.
And then, that little seed that had been sown in 1996, started germinating.
وبعد ذلك بدأت تلك البذرة التي زُرعت في 1996، بالنمو
And one day, I found myself
ويوماً ما،وجدت نفسى
entering through my boss' office and quitting my job to dedicate myself to this.
أدخل مكتب مديري وأستقيل من وظيفتي لكي أكرس نفسي لتلك الفكرة.
And so, what did I find out, right off the start?
وهكذا ماذا وجدت،مباشرة قبل البدأ ؟
I found out that it was a much more severe problem than I thought.
اكتشفت أنها كانت مشكلة أكثر تعقيداً مما ظننت
It wasn't only about these documents being complex and annoying,
لم تكن المشكلة أن تلك الوثائق معقدة ومزعجة فقط
it was the fact that Portuguese people's literacy --
لقد كانت المشكلة في معرفة البرتغاليين--
literacy is the hability to understand written documents --
المقدرة على استيعاب الوثائق المكتوبة--
is extremely low. I'm going to show you a chart about Portuguese people's literacy [rate].
ضئيلة جداً. سأريكم رسمًا بيانيًا عن أمية الشعب البرتغالي(معدل)
You know that about 10, 11% of people, in Portugal,
أنت تعرف ان تقريبا 10, 11% من الناس في البرتغال
don't know how to read nor write at all, yet.
لا يجيدون القراءة أو الكتابة مطلقاً إلى الآن
Over there are those who know, or say they know, how to read and write. So, what do we have?
فوق هذا هناك من يجيدون او يدعون أنهم يجيدونها
We have that group of red people in level 1, which is the lowest in literacy [rate].
لدينا هنا مجموعة الناس باللون الأحمر في المستوى الاول حيث الاقل قدرا من المعرفة
They are persons who are able to join letters,
وهم الاشخاص القادرون على ربط الاحرف ببعضها
but they can't, actually, understand.
ولكنهم في الحقيقة لا يستطيعون استيعابها
For example, if a person, from that red group, has to pick up
ف مثلاً لو أن شخصا من المجموعة الحمراء اضطر أن يختار
the package leaflet of a medicinal product, to give a dose of medicine to his/her child,
روشتة منتج طبي،ليعطي جرعة دواء لابنهـ(ا)
he/she can't, can't understand the information.
لن يستطيع ان يستوعب التعليمات
50% of the Portuguese. Then we have 30% more, those yellow ones,
50% من البرتغالين. ولدينا 30% آخرين، هؤلاء في المجموعة الصفراء
over there, people who get by on the daily basis.
هنا، الناس الذين يتدبرون أمورهم بشكل يومي
That is, if they don't have to read anything too new or too different, they will manage.
بحيث لو أنهم غير مضطرون لقراءة شئ جديد تماما او صعب جدا،سيتدبرون أمرهم
But, for example, if they work in a factory and a new machine arrives
ولكن مثلا لو أنهم يعملون في مصنع وماكينة جديدة وصلت للمصنع
and they have to read the machine's manual to be able to work with it, they can't do it anymore.
ويجب أن يقرأوا دليل المستخدم حتى يقدروا على التعامل معها، لن يمكنهم مره أخرى
And there they go, 80% of the Portuguese people.
80% من البرتغاليين،
Then we have a few more that can handle documents,
وبعد ذلك لدينا عدد قليل يستطيع التعامل مع الوثائق
as long as they are not too complex,
طالما أن الوثائق غير معقدة،
and we have 5% of the population that can handle really complex documents.
ولدينا 5% من السكان يستطيعون التعامل مع الوثائق المعقدة
Now, just so you don't think this is normal, that over there is Sweden.
الان،حتى لا تعتقد أن هذا امر طبيعي ففي بلد كالسويد
While we have 20% of people with the literacy considered essential for a daily basis,
بينما لدينا 20% من البرتغاليين لديهم المعرفة الضرورية ل التعامل اليومي
Sweden has 75%.
في السويد 75% من السكان.
And looking at that, what did I realize?
وبالتأمل في ذلك، ماذا أدركت؟
I realized we live in an apartheid of information.
أدركت أننا نعيش في تفرقة عنصرية للمعلومات
I realized that there's a small minority of people who has indeed access to information
أدركت ان أقلية قليلة من الناس التي تحصل فعليا على المعلومات
and can use it to their advantage and a huge majority that can't.
و تستطيع استخدامها لمصلحتها بينما الأغلبية العظمى لا تستطيع
And because they can't, they are excluded and they are impaired.
ولأنهم لا يستطيعون فهم مستبعدون و مهمشون
Let me give you an example.
دعني أوضح لك بمثال
That one is Mr. Domingos, my building's doorkeeper. Mr. Domingos started to read at the age of 27,
هذا الشخص هو السيد دومينجوس،حارس منزلي بدأ دومينجوس القراءة في عمر ال27
so, he falls in that yellow group that we have seen a little while ago.
وبالتالي هو في المجموعة الصفراء التي رأيناها منذ قليل
From time to time, I'm arriving home and he says:
من وقت ل آخر، اصل إلى منزلي ف يقول لي
"Miss Sandra!"; "Yes, Mr. Domingos."
"آنسة ساندرا"، "نعم، سيد دومينجوس؟"
"Here is a little letter." So, the deal is: when Mr. Domingos or someone in the family or in the neighbourhood
"هذا خطاب صغير" إذا فالاتفاق انه عندما يصل الى السيد دومينجوس أو اي شخص من الجوار
receives something that they don't understand, they come to me and I help them to translate it.
شئ لايستطيعون قرائته، فإنهم يأتون إلى وأساعدهم في ترجمته.
And so, that time he said to me like this:
هذه المرة دومينجوس قال لي
"Oh, Miss Sandra, I'm about to throw this away, but check it if this is important."
"آنسة ساندرا،كنت على وشك رمي هذا الخطاب لكن أقرايه لأعرف ان كان مهما"
It was very important. He had been waiting, for quite a while, to have a knee surgery
كان خطابا مهما جدا، ف قد كان يرسل خطابات لفترة طويلة، ليجري عملية في الركبة
and that was the letter of the famous surgery-bank checks. When a person is waiting for a long time,
وهذا الخطاب كان مرسلاً من مركز جراحي شهير، عندما ينتظر الشخص ل فترة طويلة
they get a bank check and with that bank check they can have that surgery in the private sector.
فإنهم يفحصون حسابه البنكي وبعدها يمكنهم اجراء العملية في القطاع الخاص
It was almost thrown away into the garbage, Mr. Domingos' letter.
لقد كان خطاب السيد دومينجوس على وشك أن يلقى في القمامة
In that same year, I've found out,
في نفس العام، وجدت أن
only 20% of people had used these surgery-bank checks.
فقط 20% من الناس استخدموا فحوصات المركز الجراحي
The other 80%, I don't believe they had been cured while they were waiting.
80% الاخرين لا أظن انهم تعالجوا بينما كانوا ينتظرون خطاب مركز الجراحات
They most likely did the same as Mr. Domingos:
أغلب الظن أنهم تصرفوا مثل دومينجوس
"Ah! What's this? I'm not understanding, it's going to the garbage".
آه ماهذا الخطاب لاأستطيع قرائته سألقيه في القمامة
They lost the opportunity to have the surgery they needed.
هذه الفئة من الناس ضاعت منها فرصة الحصول على العملية الجراحية
What happens here? When people don't understand
ماذا يحدث هنا؟ عندما لا يفهم الناس الكلمات
this has severe consequences -- to the individual, but also for the country.
لهذا الامر نتائج عديدة -- بالنسبة للفرد, لكن ايضا بالنسبة للبلد.
When I don't understand which are my rights, the benefits I can have access to,
عندما لا أفهم ما هي حقوقي والفوائد التي يمكنني الحصول عليها
I can't understand my duties and I'm not an active and participative citizen either.
فلن استطيع ان افهم واجباتي ولن اكون مواطن مؤثر ومشارك في المجتمع
Now, maybe, you are sitting there and thinking:
الآن، ربما أنتم جالسون تحدثون أنفسكم:
"Yeah, poor Mr. Domingos... Bad luck, isn't it? Me?! I'm in the green ones."
"نعم مسكين دومينجوس حظه سئ، أليس كذلك ؟ أنا؟! أنا في المجموعة الخضراء."
"I'm absolutely sure that I'm one of the green ones. I was selected to come to TED! Hum?" (Laughter)
" أنا متأكد تماما أني واحد من الخُضر. لقد تم اختياري لأكون في تيد! همم؟ (ضحك)
So the deal is: I have here some texts to read to you
إذا هكذا الأمر: لدي هنا بعض النصوص لأقرأها لكم
and I'm going to see what color are you when I finish reading.
وسأرى أي لون أنتم عندما انتهي من القراءة
So, come on, this is an automobile insurance contract. It says this:
هيا نبدأ هذا عقد تأمين سيارة، فيه الآتي:
"Unless contrary stipulation, the decease of the ensured person, the ensured capital is provided,
"مالم ينص على خلاف ذلك، في حالة وفاة الشخص المؤمن عليه يتم توفير المال المؤمن
in case of predeceasing of the beneficiary relatively to the ensured person, to the heirs of the last,
في حالة وفاة الاقارب المنتفعين قبل المؤمن عليه،تذهب النقود لورثة المؤمن عليه
in case of the simultaneous decease of the ensured person and of the beneficiary,
وفي حالة وفاة الشخص المؤمن عليه والمستفيد
to the heirs of the last". Hum? (Laughter)
فإن النقود تذهب إلى ورثة الأخير"همم؟ (ضحك)
Next, there's another one, from the medicines' package leaflet, that says the following:
التالي هناك خطاب اخر، من روشتة طبية، جاء فيه الاتي:
"Warning! It may also occur erythema, edema, vesiculation, keratolysis and urticaria."
"تحذير قد يحدث أيضاً حمامي، وذمة،تحوصل انحلال الطبقة القرنية و الأرتكاريا
Hum? Are you clear?
همم؟ هل الامر مفهوم بالنسبة لكم؟
And this one is really good. This one, I signed a renting contract to the new office on Friday
الخطاب الاخير ممتاز. وقعت عقد ايجارلمكتب جديد يوم الجمعة
and I laughed my head off.
وضحكت كثيرا
So, it said: "I, as a cosigner, assume the opportune payment of the rents,
جاء في العقد: "أنا بصفتي كفيل، اتحمل الدفع المناسب ل الايجار
waiving the benefits of the division and prior foreclosure."
والتنازل عن فوائد التقسيم والرهن المسبق
When I heard "opportune payment" ["storm payment" in Portuguese], I imagined myself bursting in there,
عندما سمعت"الدفع المناسب" ("عاصفة الدفع" بالبرتغالي) تخيلت نفسي اندفع بقوة
slamming the door and saying: "Here's the money!!!" (Laughter)
أصفع الباب وأقول " ها هي النقود!!!" (َضحك)
But it's not! (Laughter) (Applause)
ولكنه ليس كذلك(ضحك)(تصفيق)
But it's not! (Applause)
ولكنه ليس كذلك تصفيق
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So, it's this: when we leave our area of expertise --
إذا فالأمر كالتالي، عندما نخرج من دائرة خبراتنا--
and it only takes a little; there is no need to go to the string theory or something like that,
للخارج قليلا، ليس هناك حاجه ل التطرق لنظرية الأوتار او شئ مثل هذا
it only takes a little... (Laughter)
فقط خارج دائرتنا قليلا(ضحك)
What happens?
ماذا يحدث؟
We get as lost as Mr. Domingos.
لقد أصبحنا ضائعين تمام مثل دومينجوس
And these documents are not written by experts to experts,
وهذه الوثائق ليست للخبراء فقط
as the ones from the string theory.
كالوثائق التي تتحدث عن نظرية الخيط
No! These are documents written for me, these are the public documents,
لا! هذه الوثائق كتبت من أجلي، وثائق ليقرأها العامة
the public documents I need to understand in my daily life,
وثائق انا محتاج ان افهمها في حياتي اليومية
to govern myself, to live my life.
لأستطيع أن أدير شؤوني، وأعيش
These are the renting contracts, the package leaflet of the medicines.
عقود ايجار، روشتات طبية لا أكثر ولا أقل
It's all this. The electricity bills.
فواتير الكهرباء
This has to be clear, so that I can understand.
يجب ان تكون ب لغة واضحة، كي أفهمها
Because, if I can't understand, what happens?
لأنه إن لم أفهم،ماذا يحدث ؟
I make mistakes, I get wrong.
سأرتكب اخطاء
I'm going to give you an example of mistakes that were committed, bad decisions made
سأعطيكم مثالاً للأخطاء التي حدثت، والقرارات السيئة
for not being able to understand documents.
لأن الشخص كان غير قادر على فهم الوثائق
Do you remember the subprime crisis that took place in the United States?
هل تتذكرون أزمة القروض العقارية التي حدثت في أمريكا
What happened?
ماذا حدث ؟
People signed those loans to buy houses,
الناس أخذوا قروضا ليشتروى بها مساكن
without truly understanding what they were signing.
بدون أن يفهموا مالذي وقعوا عليه
Because if they knew what they were signing,
لإنهم لو عرفوا ما الذي يوقعون عليه،
they'd know that as soon as the interest rate started to rise, the monthly payment would also increase,
كانوا سيدركون أنه بمجرد أن تبدأ نسبة الفائدة بالزيادة ستزداد قيمة القسط الشهري
they wouldn't be able to pay anymore and they would end up without a house.
وماكانوا ل يستطيعوا الدفع أكثر و سينتهي بهم الأمر دون منزل
So, the rest, after that, next, everything crumbled down and we know the rest.
ولذلك فإن ماحدث بعد ذلك أن كل شئ انهار ونحن نعرف ما حدث بعد ذلك
Do you think that if there was a culture of clarity in the financial sector
هل تعتقد أنه لو وجدت ثقاقة البساطة في القطاع المالي
things would have got up to where they've got?
كانت الأمور بهذا الشكل ؟
I don't think so. So,
لا أظن ذلك،إذا--
how do you solve this problem,
كيف تعالج هذه المشكلة؟
this such big difference between the literacy [rate] of the Portuguese,
مثل هذا التباين الكبير بين معدل الأمية في البرتغال
that is down here, and the complexity of the public documents,
الموجود في الأسفل هنا، و تعقيد الوثائق الحكومية
those ones we need to understand in our daily lives, sorry,
تلك الوثائق نحتاج ان نستوعبها في حياتنا اليومية،عفوا
that are up here?
التي بالأعلى هنا
So, the first think that comes to mind is,
حسنا, الفكرة الأولى التي تأتي ل العقل هي،
"If literacy is down here, let's make it rise" -- isn't it?
"إذا كانت الأمية في الأسفل هنا، لنجعلها ترتفع--أليس كذلك ؟
Let's educate people.
هيا نعلم الناس
Let's, let's... of course we will, of course we will educate people.
هيا وهيا....بالطبع سنفعل، بالطبع سنعلم الناس.
The thing is, it's hard and it's slow. And I don't even want to imagine
الفكرة أن هذه عملية صعبه وبطيئة ولا أريد حتى أن أتخيل
how many generations it will take until we are at Sweden's level.
كم من الاجيال سنستغرق حتى نصل إلى مستوى السويد
But, besides that, it's not only because it is slow. There is another problem.
ولكن بجانب هذا، ليس لأنها بطيئة فحسب هناك مشكلة أخرى
If the language of the documents isn't simpler,
لو أن لغة الوثائق ليست أكثر بساطة،
we've already seen that people, even with a high literacy level, like you,
لقد رأينا هؤلاء الناس بالفعل، حتى بمستوى مرتفع من التعليم، مثلكم
if the language is hard, they don't get cleared,
إذا كانت اللغة صعبة، لن يفهموا ما يقرأون
they continue to be unable to understand these documents.
سيظلون غير قادرين على فهم هذه الوثائق
So, besides increasing literacy [rate], and for now,
لذا، بجانب ارتفاع معدل التعليم، وحتى هذه اللحظة
it's much more important to reduce the complexity of documents
فقد اصبح امر أكثر أهمية أن تقلل تعقيدات الوثائق
and simplify the language.
ونبسط اللغة
I'm going to show you an example.
سأريكم مثالاَ
When I talk about simplifying the language. Notice!
عندما اتحدث عن تبسيط اللغة. لاحظ معي !
On the left side of a contract:
على يسار هذا العقد :
"It is agreed that the insurance company, bla bla bla, bla bla bla, bla bla..."
"إنه متفق أن شركة التأمين..... إلخ
This is a before and after example. What do we mean with simplifying language?
هذا مثال من نوع " قبل وبعد" ماذا نقصد ب تبسيط اللغة؟
It's communicating in a simple and clear way, enabling our reader to understand it at first glance.
إنه تواصل في صورة بسيطة و مفهومة، تمكين القارئ من فهمها بمجرد النظر
What do you prefer? Before or after?
ماذا تفضلون ؟ قبل، ام بعد ؟
There isn't much doubt, is there?
لا محل للشك، أليس كذلك ؟
So, how is this achieved? How can you make the State and companies communicate
إذا، كيف تحقق هذا ؟كيف يمكنك أن تجعل الشركات والحكومة تتواصل
with citizens in a language they can understand at first glance?
مع المواطنين باللغة التي يفهمها المواطنون بمجرد النظر ل الورقة؟
There are several ways. There are countries that are going by the path of legislation.
هناك طرق عديدة لفعل هذا. هناك دول تذهب لطريق التشريعات
For example, Sweden and the United States introduced, last year, a legislation that forces
مثلا،السويد والولايات المتحدة قدموا العام الماضي، تشريعات تجبر--
the State to communicate with people in a language they can understand.
الحكومة على التواصل مع الناس بلغة يمكن للعامة فهمها.
And you think, "Well, that's normal. They are countries that are a bit ahead.
وتخاطب نفسك :"حسنا، هذا أمر عادي تلك دول تسبقنا بكثير
"Sweden, maybe, much more than the United States.
"السويد ربما أكثر كثيرا من الولايات المتحدة ."
"But they are countries that are a bit ahead.
" لكن تلك دول تسبقنا بكثير
"It would be nice if in our country there was also legislation towards that, wouldn't it be?"
"سيكون جميلاً لو كان في وطننا تشريعات بخصوص هذا الأمر، أليس كذلك ؟"
So it would. And there is! Since 1999.
لكان امراً جميلا فعلاً، وهو موجود فعلاً! منذ 1999
The Law of the Administrative Modernization says that
قانون التحديث الإداري يقول أن
the communication between the State and the people
التواصل بين الحكومة والناس
should be simple, clear, concise, meaningful, without acronyms, bla bla bla...
يحب أن يكون بلغة بسيطة،مفهومة،موجزة ومجدية وبدون أية أختصارات، إلخ
But the thing is: it is not applied. So, the question,
ولكن الأمرهو أن التشريع غير مطبق والسؤال هو:
the path of going through legislation, enforcing through legislation,
اتباع أسلوب التشريعات، الإجبار بالتشريعات
works in those countries where laws are made to be applied.
يعمل في الدول حيث القانون يوضع لكي يتم تطبيقه
Now, there is another way, the way of marketing.
الآن هناك طريقة أخرى، طريقة التسويق.
How does that work? It's like this:
كيف يعمل هذا؟ كالتالي:
private companies change their language; communicate in a clearer and simpler way,
الشركات الخاصة تغير لغتها: فتتواصل بطريقة مفهومة اكثر وبطريقة أبسط
they make a big fuss about it, consumers love it,
يصنعون ضجة ضخمة حول هذاالأمرالمستهلكون يحبون هذا
the sales rise, it works beautifully.
المبيعات تزداد،الأمر سيعمل بشكل جميل
But it works for the private sector.
ولكن بالنسبة للقطاع الخاص فقط.
Now, what is the third path, and to me, the most important one?
الآن ما هي الطريقة الثالثة وبالنسبة لي هي أكثرهم أهمية ؟
It's the path of civil movements,
طريقة الحركات المدنية،
that are based in a mentality shift.
القائمة على نقلة عقلية.
In countries where this really went forward --
في دول حيث ينجح هذا الأمر --
do you remember the English label, of the "Plain English Campaign"? --
تتذكرون الملصق الانجليزي، حملة الانجليزية؟
this is all based on a consumers' movement.
هذ كله معتمد على حركة المستخدم
So, what does it take for that civic movement to happen?
إذا مالذي يتطلبه الأمر حتى تحدث هذه الحركة المدنية؟
We need to understand two very important things:
نحن نحتاج أن نفهم أمرين مهمين:
First, wanting to understand these public documents is not a whim,
الأول الحاجة لفهم هذه الوثائق ليست بالنزوة
is not an intellectual curiosity.
وليس بالفضول الثقافي
It is a necessity that I have in my daily life.
إنها أمر ضروري أحتاجه في حياتي اليومية
And above all, it is a right, it is everyone's right.
وفوق كل شئ هي حق ، حق من حقوق كل شخص.
On this side we have: understanding is a right.
على هذا الجانب لدينا جميعا : الاستيعاب حق
And we have to understand another thing too,
وعلينا أن نفهم أمر آخر أيضاـ
which is: he who writes, has to write in order to be understood.
وهو : الشخص الذي يكتب، يجب أن يكتب بحيث يفهمه الآخرون
How do we get there?
كيف يمكننا أن نصل إلى هناك
First of all: we have to become demanding consumers and citizens.
أولاً : يجب ان نصبح مواطنين و مستخدمين متطلبين
Think it this way: next time someone gives you a document
فكر فيها هكذا : المرة القادمة عندما يعطيك شخص وثيقة
that you just simply don't understand, don't be shy,
والتي ببساطة أنت غير قادر على فهمها، لاتكن خجولاً
don't keep quiet, pretending that you are understanding everything.
لا تسكت، متظاهراً أنك تفهم كل شئ
No! Demand to understand. Ask.
لا! طالب بأن تفهم. أسأل
I know that this is not easy. Turn to the gentleman in the little suite and say:
أعرف أن هذا ليس سهلاً، انظر لشخص المهندم في بدلته الصغيره وقل :
"Look here, this contract, this part, what does this mean?"
"انظر هنا، هذا العقد، هذا الجزء، ما معنى هذا ؟
It's not easy, and perhaps it's even a bit embarrassing, isn't it?
هذا ليس سهلاً و من المحتمل حتى أن يكون محرجاً، أليس كذلك؟
But it is not. It's a sign of intelligence.
ولكنه ليس كذلك، إنه دليل على الذكاء
What do you teach your children when they have doubts in school?
ما الذي تعلمه لأطفالكم عندما يستعصي عليهم فهم أمر ما في المدرسة؟
"Don't say nothing to anyone, shut up really good and act smart."
"لا تخاطبوا أي شخص، اخرسوا جيدا وتصرفوا بلباقة"
No, you don't, right? You say:
لاأنتم لا تعلموهم صحيح أنتم تقولون لهم
"Look, when you don't understand, you put your hand up in the air and ask the teacher until you are cleared."
"انظروا عندما لا تفهمون، أرفع يدك في الهواء واسأل معلمك حتى تفهم الأمر تماما
And that is exactly what we have to do, as consumers and citizens.
وهذا ما يجب أن نفعله بالضبط كمستخدمين و مواطنين
So, next time you come across with a document you don't understand,
إذا، فالمرة القادمة التي يقابلك فيها وثيقة لا تفهمها
demand to understand, put aside your pride and ask
طالب بأن تفهم، ضع كبريائك جانباً وأسأل
until you get completely cleared.
حتى يتضح كل شئ لك تماما
Then, there's the other side, which is: "Okay, these awful documents
ثم هناك الجانب الآخر، وهو: "حسنا، هذه الوثائق الفظيعة
"which are in circulation, they don't grow on trees.
والتي هي متداولة، لا تنمو على الأشجار."
"Someone wrote them." Hum?
شخص ما كتبهم."همم ؟
Maybe, among this big group, some persons...
ربما وسط هذه المجموعة،بعض الأشخاص....
I don't know, some lawyers, some public employees -- I'm not asking you to identify yourselves,
لا أعرف بعض المحامين،بعض موظفين القطاع العام،أنا لا أطلب منكم أن تكشفوا عن أنفسكم
but I ask you to search your own conscience.
ولكن أريدكم أن تبحثوا في ضمائركم
How many times do you write documents for the general public,
كم مرة تكتبون وثائق لعامة الناس
for people that don't share your language,
لأناس لا يتشاركون معكم نفس اللغة
and you write them in a language that only you will understand?
وتكتبون لهم بلغة لن يفهمها سواكم؟
And you'll say: "Ah, that's because there is a reason, here!"
وسوف تقولون:"آه،هذا لأنه هناك سبب، ها هو!"
Dear friends, I already heard all the reasons.
أصدقائي الأعزاء،سمعت كل الأسباب
There are thousands of reasons. They go like these:
هناك آلاف الأسباب،يكونون على هذا المنوال
"Ah, it's the house's culture"; "Oh, my boss!"
"أه، إنها ثقافة المكان": "آه،إنه مديري"
"Oh, the judge! And what if this goes to court?"
"أه، القاضي! وماذا لو ذهبت هذه الورقة للمحكمة
"What you want is to destroy language. We have to educate people."
" ما تريدينه هو تدمير اللغة، يجب أن نعلم الناس"
"We can't lower the level"; bla, bla, bla...
"لايمكننا ان نتدنى بالمستوى", بلا بلا بلا
I've seen all of this. These are excuses.
لقد رأيت كل هذا، هذه كلها أعذار
A while ago, they told us about Einstein.
من فترة، أخبرونا عن أينشتاين.
Einstein said this: "If you can't write about a subject,
أينشتاين قال:" لو إنك لاتستطيع أن تكتب عن موضوع،
in a simple way, it's because, in fact, you don't understand it."
بطريقة بسيطة، فذلك لأنك في الحقيقة لا تفهم الموضوع."
So, if you... (Applause)
إذا، لو أنك.... (تصفيق)
So -- ah, ah, I don't have time! --
إذا -- آه, لم يعد لدي وقت!--
so, if you do know what you want to say -- don't you? --
إذا، لو إنك تعرف ماذا تريد أن تقول-- أليس كذلك--
you are aware of what you want to say,
أنت مدرك لما تريد أن تقوله،
you just have to do one thing: believe that it is possible to write in a simple way.
يجب عليك أن تفعل شئ واحد فقط: تصدق أنه من الممكن أن تكتب ب طريقة بسيطة
And how do you do that?
وكيف تفعل ذلك؟
It's very easy. You write to your grandmother. Hum?
إنه أمر سهل جدا. أنت تكتب ل جدتك. همم؟
You write to your grandmother. I'm going to show grandma to you.
أنت تكتب ل جدتك، سأريكم الجدة
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
You write with respect and without paternalism.
ستكتب بإحترام و بدون تعالي
And you use three techniques that I'm going to teach you. First of all:
وستستخدم ال 3 تقنيات التي سأعلمهم لك. أولا:
Start by the most important.
أبدأ بـالأمر الأكثر أهمية
Grandma has a lot to do. She is not going to read three pages to get to the main idea.
الجدة لديها الكثير من الامور لتفعلها، لن تقرأ 3 صفحات ل تصل ل الفكرة الاساسية
Start by the most important.
أبدأ بـ الأمر الأكثر أهمية
Next, use short sentences, because grandma,
الثاني، أستخدم جمل موجزة، لأن الجدة
like anyone of us,
مثل أياً منا
if you make very long sentences,
لو أنك كتبت جمل طويلة
she gets to the end and she can't remember what you said in the beginning, anymore.
فإنها تصل لنهاية الجملة ولا تتذكرما قلته في البداية
And lastly, the third, use plain words, those ones that grandma knows.
وأخيراً الثالثة، استخدم كلمات بسيطة، تلك التي تفهمها الجدة
Alright? It's easy!
جيد؟ إنه أمر سهل!
Before I leave,
قبل أن أغادر،
I would like to talk to you about "Clara" (Clear). "Clara" is a project of social responsibility.
أريد أن اتحدث معكم عن "Clara" (واضح)‘ "كلارا" مشروع إجتماعي
It has this mission: to change the way how public communication is made.
مهمتها: تغيير الطريقة التي يتم بها التواصل مع العامة .
What do we do?
ما الذي نفعله ؟
We are going to launch this year a collection of "Claro" guides,
سنقوم هذه السنة بإطلاق مجموعة من إرشادات"Claro"
that is, we are going to pick very, very, very complex subjects and put them simple.
وهي أننا سنقوم بإختيار مواضيع معقدة جدا جدا جدا ونكتبهم في صورة بسيطة
We are going to start with the "Claro" Guide of Justice.
سنبدأ ب "Claro" كتيب ارشادي في القضاء.
I think it is an area... that comes in handy. (Applause)
أعتفد أنه في هذا المجال.. سيكون له فائدة (تصفيق)
And now I'm going to follow Manuel [Forjaz]'s advise. If it's time to ask,
والآن سأتبع نصيحة كتيب (فورجاز) لو أنه الوقت ل أن أسأل,
whoever wants to sponsor the "Claro" Guide of Justice -- I don't know...
أياً كان من يريد ان يرعى مرشد"Claro" في القضاء--لا اعرف ..
for example, the EDP Foundation, or...ha? --
مثلاً, مؤسسة ال EDP, أو.. ها؟ --
come talk to me later.
تحدثوا معي فيما بعد
Another thing we will do is to grant prizes to the worse and best documents,
سنقوم بشئ أخر وهو منح جوائز ل أفضل و أسوء وثائق،
because, indeed, there are people who are working to communicate in a clearer way,
لأنه بالتأكيد ،هناك أُناس يعملون لكي يتواصلوا بطرق أكثر وضوحا
and that have to be rewarded,
ويجب أن يكافؤوا،
and there are lazy people that do nothing about it and need to be humiliated.
وهناك أناس كسولين لا يفعلون شئ ويحتاجون أن يهانوا
So, we'll give prizes to the worst and to the best.
إذا, سنعطي جوائز لالأسوء والأفضل
I'm counting on your help. (Applause)
أنا أعتمد على مساعدتكم.(تصفيق)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
We are going to launch... we are going to launch the campaign via Clara's Facebook,
سنقوم بالإنطلاق... سنقوم بالإنطلاق الحملة على صفحة Claroعلى الفيس بوك
so, send your friendship request and you'll be up to date.
أرسلوا طلبات الصداقة و ستطلعون على آخر التحديثات
But, lastly, above all, what does "Clara" want?
لكن, فوق كل شئ, مالذي تريده Claro؟
It wants to put two little things in your heads.
إنها تريد وضع شيئين صغيرين في رأسكم
The first one: demand to understand. Don't be shy.
الأول: طالبوا بأن تفهموا. لا تخجلوا
And write in order to be understood. Write to your grandma.
واكتبوا لكي يفهمكم الآخرين. أكتبوا إلى جدتكم.
And if you don't have a grandmother, write to Mr. Domingos, he will like it.
وإذا لم يكن لكم جدة, أكتبوا ل دومينجوس, سيعجبه هذا
Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً (تصفيق)